Hey, what's up, guys? My name is Cherno,
and welcome back to my C++ series.
Today, we're going to be talking about
enums in C++. So, enum is short for
enumeration, and basically all it is is
a set of values. If you want a more
practical definition, then all an enum
is is a way to give a name to a value.
So, instead of having a bunch of
integers called ABC, we can have an enum
which has the values ABC, which
correspond to integers. It also helps us
define a set of values, so that instead
of just having an integer as the type,
which of course you could assign any
integer to, you limit which values can
be assigned to what. So, without
complicating things, that's really all
that it is. It's just a way to name
values. It's very useful for when you
want to use integers to represent
certain states or certain values.
However, you want to give them a name so
that your code is more readable. At the
end of the day, an enum is just an
integer. However, in your code it looks
a little bit different, and it helps to
keep your code a bit cleaner. Let's dive
in and take a look. So, suppose that I
have three values that I wanted to take
care of. I had A, which I might set to
zero, B, which I might set to one, and
C, which I might set to two. So, I have
three values to take care of. And then,
somewhere in main, I might use my value,
and I might set it equal to one of these
three. Later on in my code, I might have
some code to check what the current
value is, and then perform some sort of
action. This is fine, however it carries
a few issues. First of all, these ABCs
are not grouped at all. Somewhere later
in your code, you might have a D, or you
might want to declare A again, and
suddenly this is a bit of an issue. But
essentially, the biggest problem here is
that these aren't grouped at all.
Furthermore, they are just integers,
meaning I can assign something like five
here, and suddenly this doesn't make any
sense anymore. We want to be able to
essentially define a type which can only
be one of these three, and is also
grouped in some kind of fashion, which
is exactly what enums can be used for.
So, instead of this, I can have my enum,
which I'll call example, and then I can
list off which values I I to have here,
such as A, B, or C. Instead of having an
integer as my type, I can now use the
enum name as an actual type. So, I can
write example value. I'm going to change
my integers to be lowercase here, just
so that I can use my enum values
properly. And you can see that I can
assign my value just like this. If I try
and assign something else, I'll get an
error because it has to be one of these
three. Now, these are just integers at
the end of the day. Keep that in mind. I
can still do a check if I If I revert
this back to B, I can still do a check
such as value equals equals one because
B does carry the value one. If you hover
your mouse over this, it'll even tell
you that B is one. You can actually
specify the value of each of these
variables as well. If you don't, by
default, the first one will be zero, and
then it will increment one by one. To
specify value, you just set it equal to
something. So, I could have this as
zero,
this is two, this is six, whatever you
really want. If you start from a number
that is not zero, such as five, and you
don't actually specify the rest of these
values, you can see that this will be
six, and this will be seven because it
will basically just start from five and
then keep going up. One other thing that
you can also do here is specify which
type of integer you want this enum to
be, and you can do so by writing a colon
and then the data type. So, for example,
an unsigned char. Enums, by default, are
32-bit integers. However, you can see in
this case, there's no need for us to use
a 32-bit value. We could We could get
away with using an 8-bit integer, such
as an unsigned char, and we'd be just
fine. And suddenly, this is taking way
less memory. You won't be able to assign
this to something like a float, of
course, because the float isn't an
integer, and it has to be an integer.
So, let's leave this as a char for our
example. So, there we go. That's
basically what an enum is. It's just a
way to give a name to certain values so
that you don't have to keep dealing with
integers and be all over the place.
Let's take a look at a real-world
example of where you might use an enum
by looking at our log class that we
started writing in the how to write a
C++ class video. If we jump over here to
our log class, you can see what we
actually ended up doing was using three
different log levels, and they were just
integers here, 0 1 2. Hopefully, you can
see that this is pretty much a perfect
candidate for an enum because we have
three values which we just used as
integers to represent a certain state.
In this case, which log level our log
will actually display. So, right over
here inside this log class, I'm going to
create a level enum. I'm going to create
error, warning, and info as possible
values. So, we're basically mirroring
this. As a matter of style, I actually
like to explicitly write equals zero.
However, that's definitely not required
because it will start at zero by
default. But again, just something I
like doing to help the readability of
the code. I'll get rid of these now.
Instead of having an int as my log
level, which I could still have, of
course, I could still assign this to
info, and since an enum is just an int,
this would still work. However, in this
case, I would be able to set any value
to log level, any integer value to log
level, and I want to restrict it to to
just being these three. So, I will
actually set this to be level. Note
restriction that I've created of it must
be these three
purely a syntactical C++ kind of
compiler enforced thing. You can get
around it really easily. It's not
something that can't physically be set,
of course. In this case, our enum is
just a four-byte integer. It's just four
bytes of memory. You can put anything
you want into that memory. However, by
setting the type to level, you're
restricting the code, so to speak, to
actually only allow levels. I'll change
my set level to take in a level. Now,
when I do these checks, they will still
work just fine. I just need to change
log level error to just be error.
Because m_log_level is this enum type,
which is an integer, I can still do
comparisons between them, which is very,
very useful for things like this. I'll
change this to say warning, and I'll
change this to say info. The other thing
to change is here is the log.set_level.
Instead of being log.log_level_error,
which used to be that integer, it now
simply becomes log error because we have
an enum value called error inside our
log namespace. Note that this enum level
is not a name space in itself. There is
something called an enum class, which we
will talk about in another video.
However, just for regular enums, this
level isn't really a name space, so you
can't use it as one. Which means that
this error, warning, and info simply
exists inside this log class. As you can
see, I can set it to something like
warning as well, and everything's fine.
Now, you might have noticed the error
doesn't actually work, and it gives us
an error. The reason this is happening
is because we actually have a function
called error as well, so same name. And
I've set this up deliberately to show
you what happens if you have a
conflicting name. Now, in this case,
unfortunately, that wouldn't work
because when we try and refer to things
like error here, it doesn't know if
we're referring to the function or not.
So, we definitely can't have something
called error here, unfortunately, if we
want to have a function with the same
name. So, for now, we can just add a
level prefix to the enum, which, by the
way, is very, very common practice, so
that we know exactly what we're
referring to. Since this name doesn't
really mean much in the scope of things.
So, I'll set this equal to level info,
this to level error, this to level
warning,
and this to level info.
And now, of course, I don't need this. I
can get rid of this and just set this
equal to level error. If I run my code,
you can see that I would get the result
that I expect, where only error is
printing, of course, because we've set
our level to be error. So, there you go.
Enums just essentially exist to make our
lives easier and to make our code
cleaner. They are just integers behind
the scenes, and you can use them pretty
much in any way like integers. There are
many, many uses for enums, which we will
cover in future videos. We'll definitely
talk about enum classes as well in
another video. But, essentially,
whenever you have a set of values which
you want to represent numerically, an
enum is probably the way to go. I'll see
you guys next time. Goodbye.